[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have another question that's sent to me by some friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll try my best to answer it for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's concerned about forgiveness, trying to forgive people, and he's finding that difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, his question is, I'm finding it very difficult to forgive some people in my life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having done terrible things to others in the past, I know it's also my karma to experience this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, firstly, yeah, that's... you might have done some bad things to people in your life in the past, and the result of those actions, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: This might be one of those results.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, other people are doing bad things to you, but that's not necessarily the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other people might be doing bad things to you because that's just how the world is.
[SPEAKER_00]: People do bad things to others because they're there to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: People do bad things because they themselves are acting out of lust, anger and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're in that world with them, so you're going to get affected by that, their actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not necessarily from your past actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he also says, I know that they will also get the results of their actions, which is true, acting out of hurting others, trying to be, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Being cruel towards others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what you will get, immediate result of that, is a cruel mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, is a cruel mind peaceful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a happy mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a agitated mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unsettled.
[SPEAKER_00]: A cruel mind cannot be composed, settled, at peace, calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those states are not there for a cruel mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a person who is cruel, those states of mind cannot exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as they are acting out of their ill-will, they cannot have peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is suffering right then and there for that person.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the result of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this person also says, he can't help but fantasize about revenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he can't stop fantasizing about revenge, because something has happened to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He feels pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he continues to feel that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that pain came about through the circumstances of others doing certain things to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just wants to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he starts to hate on the others and blame them for that pain that he suffers.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you could just destroy those others, then the pain would be gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the kind of logic there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you had to destroy the others, is there still a possibility that others will now harm you?
[SPEAKER_00]: In the future, will pain arise in the future that you will hate, that you will feel pain, you know, suffer in regards to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can destroy these people, teach them a lesson, and then tomorrow someone else does something, and you feel pain again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, not even someone else does something, just the weather changes, it's raining outside, you feel pain again.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you going to do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't take revenge on the weather, on the clouds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pain, what I'm trying to say is that pain is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That feeling of pain is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no amount of changing your external circumstances is going to solve that fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are a human being who feels pleasure, pain, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And feeling pain is just part of the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain doesn't make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is your attitude towards that pain that makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will always be something in the world that's going to be disagreeable somewhere along the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to cause you pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if your attitude towards that pain is, I want to get rid of it, I hate it, I must destroy it, you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's clear what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: That attitude must be changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that attitude is changed, let go of, and you let you endure the pain, you don't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just discern it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Painful mind state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to fight it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to get angry at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to get angry at the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you will find is that that pain will just change, eventually, like it always has.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arises and then disappears, while you're doing this and that and the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just sit down, do nothing, and you will see that pain
[SPEAKER_00]: Arise, it'll be there, and it'll be gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll come and go on its own accord.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's corresponding to certain things sometimes, but sometimes you walk outside and it's raining, and it's... you feel pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you walk outside, it's raining, and there's pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pleasure and pain, that feeling, comes and it's just rising and ceasing on its own accord, alongside everything else you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't really matter where this feeling comes from and what's the difference between perception and feeling and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, really, the key thing here is, if you are getting angry,
[SPEAKER_00]: At that pain, you are going to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a guarantee.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're lustful for pleasure, you are suffering, then and there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you remove that resistance towards pain, that anger and fighting towards pain, you will immediately feel a kind of release of
[SPEAKER_00]: Release from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Small releases.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the pressure will ease off.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you stop fighting pain, you feel the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you're suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But stop fighting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: See it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, when you can do that kind of thing, you can step back and just have some faith to step back and stop fighting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just basic logic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, if I'm angry, I'm fighting that suffering, so let me stop doing that in regards to pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see what happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will feel calmer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will feel a bit... You will feel at peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: A little bit, at least.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will start to learn something there that
[SPEAKER_00]: I can actually do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have the ability to endure pain, you know, mental pain, without acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I do this even more?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I do this all the time?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I'm mindful of feeling all the time like this?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's mindfulness of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overwhelming feeling with your discernment, so to speak, and your peacefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your non-hate, and your non-lust, and your non-destruction, overwhelming feeling, with those qualities, and you will get stronger in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those qualities will be even stronger and stronger and stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be able to discern the nature of feelings eventually, seeing them as anatta,
[SPEAKER_00]: But I won't get... we won't talk about that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, you don't... you can... you don't have to forgive.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to forgive the people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you think that forgiveness is going to free you from that suffering of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That suffering of the pain is caused by your craving against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no amount of forgiving others, forgiving the weather, is going to solve that issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got to solve that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got to stop that craving towards pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it doesn't matter what others do to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find yourself in a difficult situation where someone does something horrible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you are above feeling, or you... you can endure feeling in the way I've described, well, nothing can get to you then.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't suffer anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what people do to you, which is the ultimate safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you no longer can even take that feeling personally anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not taking feeling personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But to get to that stage, you need to step back and see the nature of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just start, ah, feelings are mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take feelings personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you need to endure them first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to not act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not try to get pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not fight against pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is going to be difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is the pathway that you need to travel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's difficult, but where you will lead... where it will lead you to is complete.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely being untouched, unpressured, ever again by what is felt.